<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The schoole of beastes; intituled, the good housholder, or the oeconomickes. Made dialogue-wise, by M. Peter Viret, translated out of French into English, by I.R.</title>
            <title>Metamorphose Chrestienne. Part 2. English</title>
            <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105385</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841114</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841114</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5673</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 944:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The schoole of beastes; intituled, the good housholder, or the oeconomickes. Made dialogue-wise, by M. Peter Viret, translated out of French into English, by I.R.</title>
                  <title>Metamorphose Chrestienne. Part 2. English</title>
                  <author>Viret, Pierre, 1511-1571.</author>
                  <author>I. B., fl. 1585.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert VValde-graue,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by I.B., of Part 2 of: Viret, Pierre. Metamorphose chrestienne.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Domestic relations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Households --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Animals --  Anecdotes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5673:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5673:1"/>
            <p>THE SCHOOLE <hi>of Beaſtes,</hi> Intituled, the <hi>good Houſholder, or the</hi> Oeconomickes.</p>
            <p>¶ Made Dialogue-wiſe, by M. PETER VIRET, tranſlated out of French into Engliſh, by I. R.</p>
            <p>GOD IS MY DEFENDER</p>
            <figure>
               <p>GOD IS MY HELPER</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON; <hi>Printed by Robert <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-graue</hi> 1585</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:5673:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5673:2"/>
            <head>The Contentes of this <hi>Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Haue intituled this Dialogue, the good Houſeholder, or the <hi>Oeconomicks,</hi> becauſe I make compariſon in the ſame, of the good and euil houſeholders with the beastes, which knowe best to prouide for their nouriſhment and conſeruation, aſwell of them as of their yong.</p>
            <p>And becauſe alſo that the Philoſophers, haue called the knowledge of wel and wiſe gouerning the houſes and families, by the name of <hi>Oeconomicks,</hi> and alſo the bokes which they haue compoſed and made of ſuch matter: It ſeemeth to me that this title agreeth very wel to this Dialogue. As touching the principal matters whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5673:3"/>
are intreated of in it, firſt I declare, in what degree of humanitie we may put the wyſest men of this worlde, which are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the true knowledge of God, and without true religion, and which neuertheleſſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne themſelues more wiſely then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as touching their houſholdes and worldly affayres.</p>
            <p>And therefore, I compare the reaſon and prudence of men, with the ſame of Beaſtes, touching their domeſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, and chiefely with the ſame of the <hi>Antes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And proſecuting that matter, I ſpeake of the transformation of <hi>Antes</hi> into men.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes I declare howe <hi>Salomon</hi> doth ſend vs vnto the ſchoole of the <hi>Ants, Connies, Graſhopers</hi> and <hi>Spyders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by that occaſion, I ſpeake of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe Beaſtes, and do declare what thinges we ought to learne of them.</p>
            <p>Item, of the compariſon of the workes of thoſe Beaſtes, and of thoſe of men.</p>
            <p>Of the transformation of <hi>Arachna,</hi> and of <hi>Acteon,</hi> and of the prouidence of God, the whiche manifeſteth it ſelfe in the
<pb facs="tcp:5673:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nature of the brute beaſtes, and cheefely in thoſe which are the leaſt.</p>
            <p>And becauſe that the cheefeſt thing that is required in a good houſholder, is the amitie and loue of the huſbande and the wife, the one towardes the other, and the care that the fathers and mothers of the familie, ought to haue of their children and families: I make a certaine diſcourſe, touching the nature of the Beaſtes whiche haue ſome ſinguler gyfte more then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue, in the coniunction of the male with the female, and in the affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their litle ones, and the care they haue of them.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſpeake, cheefely of the nature of the <hi>Pigeons,</hi> of the <hi>Swallows,</hi> of the <hi>Partridge,</hi> of the <hi>Hares,</hi> and of the <hi>Hedge-hogges,</hi> touching that point? and make compariſon with thoſe men, which doo not their dutie ſo well towardes theirs, as thoſe beaſtes doo in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.</p>
            <p>I doo adde alſo vnto thoſe, the <hi>Halſion</hi> a Byrde of the Sea. And afterwardes I do alſo make mention of certayne fiſhes, and
<pb facs="tcp:5673:4"/>
certayne Sea beaſtes, as the <hi>Phyces,</hi> the <hi>Lamprey,</hi> the <hi>Tortice,</hi> the ſea <hi>Calfe,</hi> and the <hi>Crocodiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after to conclude, I declare what is the office of fathers and mothers towards their children, according to the doctrine of Saint <hi>Paule.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:5673:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE of the ſchoole of Beaſtes, Intituled the good houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, or the Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mickes.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The ſpeakers.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tobias.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theopharſtus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOV TAKEST IN hande a worke <hi>(Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus)</hi> the which ſhal not be greatly to the honour of men, if thou canſt atayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that to whiche thou haſt bounde thy ſelfe. For yf the beaſtes do better their office accordyng to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:5"/>
then men doe theirs, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue more to be called reaſonable, then men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>I doubte not but that at the firſt ſight, many will finde that which I haue ſayde to be very ſtrang. But ſith that the ſpirite of God doth ſende vs ſo often tymes vnto the ſchoole of beaſtes in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Men are ſent to the ſchole of Beaſtes.</note> we may thereby iudge, howe much men ought to eſteeme and ſet by them ſelues, ſeeing they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo euyl their office, that they muſt be ſent vnto the beaſtes, for to learne of them what they ought to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>I pray thee declare vnto vs the places of the holy ſcriptures, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing with that matter for to make vs better to vnderſtand what is that ſchoole of beaſtes, to whiche the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God ſendeth vs, as thou ſaieſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt marke, what the Lord ſayd by the mouth of <hi>Iob,<note place="margin">Iob. 21 7.</note> aſke the Cattell, and they ſhal informe thee: The Foules of the ayre, and they ſhall tell thee: ſpeake to the errth, and it ſhall ſhewe thee: Or too the fiſhes of
<pb facs="tcp:5673:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Sea, and they ſhall certifie thee.</hi> Nowe ſeeing that <hi>Iob</hi> doth ſende vs to the beaſtes, generally for to bee taught by them: I will nowe bring foorth more ſpecially and perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly the Doctors &amp; Maiſters, which are ſet forth vnto vs by the worde of God, in this ſchoole of the beaſtes which we ſpeake of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>With which of the beaſtes wilt thou begin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>With that which is the leaſt of al.<note place="margin">Cood houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders and pollitike me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Thou knoweſt that men doo greatly eſteeme thoſe whiche knowe beſt to gouerne them ſelues in this worlde, and which are pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and wiſe, to gather together great ſtore of earthly treaſures, and for to gouerne wel their houſe, A Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a Cuntrie, or a whole Realme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Such men are ſo much eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amonge others, that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they do not eſteeme any other to be wyſe, prudent nor good men but onely thoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>It is euen ſo as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: But when al ſhalbe wel conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:5673:6"/>
what compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is there in ſuche matter, betweene ſuch men and the Authour, and wherein are they to be preferred before the <hi>Antes?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Ante.</note> I doo not yet ſpeake of other beaſts, which according to their nature, knowe to prouide althinges for their affayres, as needeth for their conſeruation. But I take this ſame, whiche is the leaſt that may be: And yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhe hath ſo much induſtrie, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,<note place="margin">Prou. 6.6.</note> and diligence in her, that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was not aſhamed to ſende the ſluggard vnto her ſchoole. It were a thing incredible, if we had not the experience for a witnes, that ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle beaſtes, could carie ſuche heauie burthens as they do, and that they can heape togeather the thinges as they do for their prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; to kepe among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch order as they keepe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>I would to God that men in their behalfe, knewe to keepe ſo good order amongeſt them ſelues. What ſayeſt thou <hi>Ierome?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhouldeſt haue yet better occaſion to ſay ſo as thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
if thou haddeſt heard that which <hi>Plinie</hi> and <hi>Plutarke,</hi> beſides other wiſe men, haue written of the nature of thoſe litle Beaſtes, and ſhouldeſt be yet leſſe abaſhed,<note place="margin">Prou. 6.6.</note> for that <hi>Solomon</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them for myſtreſſes to the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhalt doe me great pleaſure, to declare vnto me what thinges thoſe two Authours haue written, whom thou namedſt vnto me but now. For I vnderſtand that they were both of them very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men; and that they haue written very wel of thoſe matters, of which they haue ſpoken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>I wil begin with <hi>Plinie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plini. lib. cap 30. Ariſto. lib de animalib. 9 cap. 38 The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of the Ants. and their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and induſtrie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> who hath written maruelous things. Firſt he confeſſeth that there is among them, the order and faſhion of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, &amp; a remembrance and care. But amongſt al their other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, is it not a paſtime, to ſee them bite the burthens that they wil cary? If they bee too great and heauie for them, they turne them ſelues backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, and ſtay it with their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb facs="tcp:5673:7"/>
thruſt it forwarde with their hinder feete. And to the ende that the ſeedes whiche they hyde in the earth, ſhoulde not growe, and take roote, they byte it before they lay it vp in their Garners and ſtore hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And if the graynes be too great, and that they cannot eaſily enter in at their holes, they deuide it in the myddeſt. If they be moyſt or wette with the rayne, they do bring them out and drye them. Alſo they labour in the night, when the Moone is at the full, and ceaſe and leaue of when ſhe is in the waine. Wherein they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that they vnderſtande ſome thing in Aſtronomie. But what labor &amp; diligence is there in their workes? And for that that they do fetch and gather their prouiſion from diuerſe places, &amp; that the one knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the other,<note place="margin">Plinie liber. 11. &amp;. 30. The faires of the Ants.</note> 
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> witneſſeth, that they haue certayne dayes of fayres, for to knowe the one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Euery man may thinke what courſe and what diligence there is then amongſt them. But if one mark
<pb facs="tcp:5673:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
them nerely, wil he not ſay, that they ſpeake together, and do aſke and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the one the other? Do we not ſee the ſtones and hard works made ſmoothe, and holes worne in them thorowe the ofte going too and fro about their worke? Wherin we may wel knowe how much the diligence and exerciſe is worthy, and can doo in euery thing. For if the feete of thoſe litle beaſtes can make hollowe and ſmooth the hard ſtones, thorow their ofte going and comming to &amp; fro, what may the continuall labour &amp; trauaile of men do? It is not then without cauſe that the Greekes ſaid in a prouerbe,<note place="margin">A prouerbe.</note> 
                  <hi>exerciſe can doe all thinges.</hi> But beſides al that,<note place="margin">Exerciſe and diligence can doe all thinges.</note> it is alſo written of them, that they do burye the one the other, as men do. Theſe thinges make me to thinke,<note place="margin">The buriall of the Ants.</note> that the <hi>Poetes</hi> haue fayned, that the people called <hi>Myrmidons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plinie. lib. 11. Cap. 30.</note> came from the <hi>Antes</hi> whiche were chaunged into men? Becauſe of their induſtrie and labour,<note place="margin">Antes tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Myrmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons.</note> and of that prudence and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection that they haue, which is next
<pb facs="tcp:5673:8"/>
to the nature of men. For thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haue ben much eſteemed among the <hi>Poetes,</hi> and chiefely becauſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Achilles ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ili.</note> whiche was their captayne in the warres of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Whiche of all the poetes hath ſpoken, of that transformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ouid</hi> maketh a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in his Metamorphoſes, in whiche he declareth howe that the people of king <hi>Aeacus,</hi> being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcomfited thorowe the great plague &amp; death, was reſtored againe by the meanes of the Antes, whiche were chaunged into men, of whiche transformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſpeaketh after this maner, as it is tranſlated into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe miter.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid. meta. lib. 7</note>Hard by vs as it hapt that tyme,</l>
                  <l>there was an Oken tree,</l>
                  <l>With spreaded armes as bare of boughs,</l>
                  <l>as lightly one ſhall ſee.</l>
                  <l>This tree (as al the reſt of Okes,)</l>
                  <l>was ſacred vnto Ioue,</l>
                  <l>And ſprouted of an Acorne which,</l>
                  <l>was fet from Dodon groue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5673:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Here markt we how the pretie Antes,</l>
                  <l>the gatherers vp of grayne.</l>
                  <l>One folowing other al along,</l>
                  <l>in order of a trayne.</l>
                  <l>Great burthens in their litle mouthes.</l>
                  <l>did painefully ſuſteyne.</l>
                  <l>And nimbly vp the rugged barke,</l>
                  <l>their beaten path mayntayne.</l>
                  <l>As wondring at the ſwarme I ſtoode,</l>
                  <l>I ſayde, O father deare,</l>
                  <l>As many people geue thou me,</l>
                  <l>as Antes are creeping here.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And by and by afterwardes, follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing on his purpoſe, he commeth to the transformation of them, and ſaid as foloweth.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Me thought I ſawe the ſelfe ſame Oke,<note place="margin">Ouid meta. lib. 7</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>with al his boughes and twiges,</l>
                  <l>And al the Piſmires creeping ſtill,</l>
                  <l>vpon his taunts and ſpriges.</l>
                  <l>Which trembling with a ſodayne brayde,</l>
                  <l>theſe harneſt folke of threwe.</l>
                  <l>And ſhed them on the ground about,</l>
                  <l>who on the ſodayne grewe.</l>
                  <l>In bignes more and more,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5673:9"/>&amp; from the earth them ſelues did lift,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoode vpright againſt the tree,</l>
                  <l>and ther withal did ſhift.</l>
                  <l>Their neygernes, and cole blacke hue,</l>
                  <l>and number of their feete:</l>
                  <l>And clad their lymmes with ſhape of man,</l>
                  <l>away my ſleepe did fleete.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And by and by afterwardes, <hi>Ouid</hi> him ſelfe expoundeth and declareth the cauſe wherfore that tranſforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was fayned, as I euen nowe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and therefore he bringeth in <hi>Aecus</hi> ſpeaking after this maner.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid meta. lib. 7.</note>And I (my vowes to Ioue perfourmd,)</l>
                  <l>my Citie did deuide:</l>
                  <l>Among my newe inhabiters,</l>
                  <l>and gaue them land beſide.</l>
                  <l>Which by deceaſe of ſuch as were,</l>
                  <l>late owners of the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Lay waſt, and in remembrance of,</l>
                  <l>the race whereof they came.</l>
                  <l>The name of <hi>Emetes</hi> I them gaue,</l>
                  <l>their perſons you haue ſeene:</l>
                  <l>Their diſpoſition is the ſame,</l>
                  <l>that earst in them hath beene.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:5673:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>They are a ſparing kinde of folke.</l>
                  <l>on labour wholy ſet:</l>
                  <l>A gatherer, and a horder vp,</l>
                  <l>of ſuch as they do get.</l>
                  <l>Theſe fellowes being like in yeeres,</l>
                  <l>and courrage of the minde,</l>
                  <l>Shal goe awarfare when aſſoone,</l>
                  <l>as that the eſterne winde.</l>
                  <l>Which brought you hither luckely,</l>
                  <l>(the Eaſterne winde was it,</l>
                  <l>That brought them thyther,)</l>
                  <l>turning to the Sotherne coaſt do flit.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ouid,</hi> hath partly taken the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this fable, becauſe that <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mex</hi> ſignifieth in Greeke an <hi>Ante,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Myrmex.</note> of which name it ſemeth that the name of the <hi>Myrmidons</hi> is taken,<note place="margin">The cauſe of this fable &amp; of the name of the myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midons.</note> for the cauſe which hath beene alredy alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by <hi>Ouid</hi> him ſelfe. And therein <hi>Ouid</hi> hath ſhewed, howe muche hee hath eſteemed the <hi>Antes</hi> and their labours, when he did not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thoſe men vnto them, which he thought to be moſt induſtrious and geuen to labour, but alſo hath fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made of the <hi>Ants.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5673:10"/>
As though he woulde ſay, that men are not naturally ſo induſtryous and geuen to labour, as the <hi>Antes,</hi> and that the <hi>Myrmidons</hi> ſhould not bee ſo induſtrious, if they had not beene before <hi>Antes,</hi> and that they had ben taken from their kynde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Seeing that the <hi>Myrmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> are called by that name, for the cauſe thou ſpeakeſt of, that name cannot by right be geuen vnto the ſluggardes, whom <hi>Solomon</hi> doth ſend vnto the <hi>Ante.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>It is eaſie to iudge. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I haue in effect declared, that which <hi>Plinie</hi> hath written, of the nature of the <hi>Antes,</hi> it remayneth now, that I do alſo declare that which <hi>Plutarke</hi> witneſſeth of it.<note place="margin">The witnes of Plutarke of the nature of the Ante.</note> For he doth not onely accord with <hi>Plinie,</hi> in that that he hath written, but alſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth more ſpecially and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly, the great vertues whiche are in theſe litle beaſtes, of whom he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth after this ſorte.<note place="margin">Plutat. in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus.</note> But as it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posſible (ſayth he) to ſpeake worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ynough of the diſcipline, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall
<pb facs="tcp:5673:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
induſtrie of the <hi>Antes,</hi> yet we muſt not paſſe without ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omewhat of them. Nature hath no <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reater and more excellent mirror of great and excellent things. For in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it ſhineth the ſignet of all vertue, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in a pure litle droppe. That com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication that they haue among <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem ſelues, is the Image of amitie: <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſtrength and liuelines that they haue in their labours and trauayles, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s an Image of force and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. To conclud, they haue a great manie of ſeeds and witneſſes of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, of prouidence &amp; of Iuſtice. Nowe although that <hi>Cleanthes</hi> eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not that the beaſtes were endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d with reaſon, yet neuertheleſſe, he confeſſed, that he did ſee on a tyme <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſpectacle, that is, that certayne <hi>Antes</hi> went to an ant-heape, carrying <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dead <hi>Ante,</hi> from which ante-heape <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certayne other <hi>Ants.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fterwards when they had as it were ſpoken together, they went agayne <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and did ſo twyſe or thriſe. In the ende they brought a worme, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5673:11"/>
was the price as it ſhould ſeme, for to redeme the dead. The which worme was taken by thoſe which did bring the dead <hi>Ante:</hi> the which they gaue vnto the others and went their way. But now euery one may know their beneuolence when they meete the one the other: when thoſe that are emptie, geue place vnto thoſe that are laden, that they may paſſe the more eaſily: When they deuide into many peeces, a burthen that is too heauie for them eyther to beare or to drawe:<note place="margin">The aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie and Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Antes.</note> when they ſet the corne in the ſonne to drye it. It is a ſigne of rayne, as <hi>Aratus</hi> eſteemeth, when the <hi>Ante</hi> bringeth out of her hole and denne al her egges, Although that ſome ſay that they be not egges,<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the graines and prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> but the frute which they bring foorth, when they feele and perceaue that it waxeth muſtie. And for that cauſe they feare leaſt it ſhoulde waxe rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And the care that they haue leaſt their graynes ſhould not ſpring and grow, ſurpaſſeth al mens vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: And that care alſo whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5673:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they haue, that their ſeedes whiche they haue layde vp in their hole and denne, ſhould abyde drye and not rotten, fearing leaſt ſodenly they ſhould waxe moyſt, and become like mylke, and that being moyſtened with the moyſtnes of the place, it ſhoulde returne agayne into graſſe. To the end then that their graynes ſhould not growe and ſpring: and that ſo by that meanes they ſhoulde not looſe their nouriſhment and foode, but that it may continue and they lyue, they bite the nable of the grayne, which is the part by which it ſpringeth and groweth, and gelde it long time before. Nowe ſome ſaye that the firſt deſcending, and next to the entring in of their holes, is not right and ſtraight foorth, and that there is no other beaſt which can go in at it: But that it is croked &amp; with many turninges, hauing many croſſe wayes, the which is made into their holes and dennes. The one is that, where they make their aſſemblies &amp; parliaments. The other celle or hole
<pb facs="tcp:5673:12"/>
is, that where they laye vp their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for al the yeere: And the third is the buriall place for the dead. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde that which <hi>Plutarke</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the <hi>Antes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Sith that <hi>Solomon</hi> hath ſette foorth for the ſluggrdes,<note place="margin">Prouerbs. 6.</note> the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Ante,</hi> I doubt not but that ſhe is very laborious and diligent. But I knowe not whether we ought to beleeue all that whiche <hi>Plinie</hi> and <hi>Plutarke</hi> haue written.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>Whether al that whiche they haue written be true or no, I referre me to them-ſelues. But yet neuertheleſſe, I think that they haue not written without ſome reaſon that, that they do teſtifie: Beſids ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce witneſſeth, at the leaſt in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e part, the thinges the whiche they do witneſſe. But ſith that we haue heard their witneſſe, let vs now heare what <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> will ſay more vpon that place, the whiche he hath alredie alledged out of <hi>Solomon,</hi> touching this mattet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhalbe good that we heare the very words of <hi>Solomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the better to vnderſtande the doctrine, the whiche he woulde geue vs to vnderſtand by the ſame.<note place="margin">Prouerb. 6.6 The ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſent to the ſchole of the Ante.</note> 
                  <hi>Goe to the</hi> Emits (ſayth he) <hi>thou ſluggard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider her waies and learne to be wiſe. She hath no guide, no teacher, no leader: yet in the Sommer ſhe prouideth her meate, and gathereth her foode together in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt. Howe long wilt thou ſleepe thou ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhe man? when wilt thou ariſe out of thy ſleepe? Yea ſleepe on ſtill a litle, ſlomber a litle, fold thy hands together yet a litle, that thou mayeſt ſleepe: So ſhal pouertie come vnto thee as one that trauaileth by the way, and neceſſitie like a weaponed man.</hi> And in an an other place, marke what he ſpeaketh, not onely of the <hi>Ante,</hi> but alſo of certayne other litle Beaſtes, which are not of any great ſtrength.<note place="margin">Prou 30.24</note> 
                  <hi>There be foure thinges in the earth</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the whiche are very litle: but in wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they exceede the wiſe. The</hi> Emmets <hi>are but a weake people, yet gather they their meate together in the Harueſt. The</hi> Conies <hi>are but a feeble folke, yet make they their couches among the rockes. The</hi> Graſhoppers <hi>haue not a guide, yet goe
<pb facs="tcp:5673:13"/>
they foorth together by heapes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the</hi> Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>laboreth with her handes, and that in the Kinges palace.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore doth <hi>Salomon</hi> ſet foorth the feblenes of thoſe beaſtes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophra.</speaker>
               <p>It is to take from the ſlugardes and idle perſons,<note place="margin">The excuſe aſ the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardes and ſlothfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</note> all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes which they might aleadge for to excuſe their ſlugiſhnes and ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. For although that theſe litle beaſts are feeble &amp; weak, &amp; that they haue no king nor Prince for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and conduct them: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, that doth not let and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them to do their workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>Is, that the cauſe, why hee ſaid, that they had no guide?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>In ſpeaking the ſame, he giueth two aduertiſementes vnto men, the which are worthy to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For on the one ſide, he rebuketh them for that they do nothing but thorowe compulſion, and that they cannot yet do their dutie, although they be incited and driuen forwards by many meanes, wherein they haue a great aduantage, which the beaſtes
<pb facs="tcp:5673:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue not. For they haue none other maſter nor myſtres to teach them, but the nature which God gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with whiche they doo better keepe their eſtate, then men doo in that with which they were firſt created of God. And on the other ſide, he doth alſo admoniſhe the Princes and all ſuperiours,<note place="margin">The office of princes</note> not to ſuffer thoſe to liue idlely whom they haue in charge, &amp; to keepe and defend them. And by that he ſpeaketh of the <hi>Conyes,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh the raſhnes and foliſh hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men.<note place="margin">Raſhnes.</note> And by that he ſpeaketh of the <hi>Graſhoppers,</hi> he rebuketh them of their diſobedience towardes their maieſtrates. And by the <hi>Spider,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence.</note> he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſheth that thoſe which haue the charge of the common wealth or publicke thinges,<note place="margin">Care.</note> ought to be more careful and vigilant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinks that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſay that thoſe which are in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke office, and in Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces houſes, ought to be more careful and diligent then any other, after the example of the <hi>Spider,</hi> who is not idle
<pb facs="tcp:5673:14"/>
in the Kinges palace. And yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, thoſe houſes are commonly the ſchooles of the greateſt Idlenes that is in the worlde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>And therfore God doth ſend them the ſpiders, for to rebuke and checke them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>And therefore I thinke that that is the cauſe wherefore the Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are ſo muche dryuen away with their copwebs,<note place="margin">A Prouerbe.</note> wherefore men ſay in a common prouerbe, That the <hi>Spider</hi> hath taken vp her lodging with the poore men, &amp; the Goute in the riche mens houſes, in whiche ſhe may take beſt reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs leaue of that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and come agayne vnto <hi>Salomon,</hi> who ioyneth here theſe foure beaſts, who notwithſtanding they are but lytle of bodie, yet neuertheleſſe they do playnely ſhewe, that they haue a maruaylous naturall wyſedome, by which they paſſe and excell the ſame of the wyſe men. Then as he woulde that we ſhould learne of the <hi>Ante,</hi> to be diligent, geuen to labour, and well
<pb facs="tcp:5673:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
foreſeeing to our affayres: So he ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs vnto the <hi>Connies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and that that they do teache vnto man.</p>
                     <p>A ſure dwelling.</p>
                  </note> that we may learne by their example, not onely to be diligent, and geuen to labour, but alſo to ſeeke for a ſure &amp; firme dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For notwithſtanding that the <hi>Connies</hi> are without ſtrength and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, inſomuch that they can doo none other thing, but to flye at the baye and barking of the leaſt Dogge in the worlde: yet neuertheleſſe they are ſuch continuall diggers and ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that they bring it to paſſe in the end, that they do cleaue a ſunder and make hollow the ſtones and rockes, for to lodge them ſelues therein, and their yong ones with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſayde in the Pſalmes. <hi>The rockes are a refuge for the Connies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 104.18.</note> For they knowe very well howe to make their Caues and dennes, and to finde out fitte and ſure places for the ſame: and they are very diligent for to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for their meate and their yong-ones, of which they are ſo fruitefull,<note place="margin">Pli. lib. 8.55.</note> that ſometimes the Balearians were conſtrayned to demaunde ayde and
<pb facs="tcp:5673:15"/>
ſouldiers of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> againſt thoſe, fearing leaſt they woulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Cuntry, as they haue ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme deſtroyed Cities. <hi>Nowe ſeeing that we haue not here any abyding and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Cittie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> 
                  <hi>but do ſeeke another: where may we find a ſure habitation &amp; dwelling, but in the holie Citie of the celeſtiall Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.3. Apo. 21.22. Pſal. 118.19. Math. 16.21. 1. Cor. 11.34 Pro. 18.10. Ephe. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>of which God is the wall? And in the Church of Ieſus Chriſt, which is the houſe of God builded vpon the ſure ſtone and ſure rocke? For the name of God is a ſtrong bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke and a ſure forſtreſſe. Wherefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we haue Ieſus Chriſt the ſure ſtone which is the foundation of the holie Citie of the celeſtiall Ieruſalem, and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles we are admoniſhed that we muſt not be fearefull and cowardes, how great febleneſſe ſoeuer be in vs:</hi> But that we employ our ſelues euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the gyftes which we haue receyued of God, hauing alwaies our refuge vnto that ſtone and Rocke. Thoſe then whiche put all their truſt and affyance in the vayne and brittle thinges of this worlde, and in their ryches, honours, parentages, and in
<pb facs="tcp:5673:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the vayne ceremonies and traditions of men, and in the workes of their handes, are not ſo wyſe and prudent as the <hi>Connies,</hi> but are thoſe fooles of whom Ieſus Chriſt ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.26.</note> 
                  <hi>which builded their houſes vpon the Sandes.</hi> For ſith that they are not builded vpon the worde of God, and that they do not kepe it in their hartes, their buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wil fall downe vpon them. The which thing we ought wel to learne, not onely of the <hi>Connies,</hi> but alſo of the <hi>Moules.</hi> For <hi>Varro</hi> witneſſeth,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 8.29. mart in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popho.</note> that in <hi>Theſſalie,</hi> a Citie, was ouerthrowen by the <hi>Moules:</hi> And another in <hi>Spaine</hi> by the <hi>Connies.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>If theſe litle beaſtes can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow and deſtroy the buildings, edified and builded by men, we may wel know what fortreſſe one can find whiche can reſiſte the power &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>We haue yet to note, that beſides al that, the <hi>Connies</hi> may bragge &amp; boſt them ſelues that they haue taught men, the maner to make mynes, holes and caues vnder the
<pb facs="tcp:5673:16"/>
ground, for to vndermine and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe Townes, Caſtles and fortreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And therefore the mynes and Caues that men make vnder the ground, keepeth yet the name of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies among the Latines. For they cal them <hi>Cuniculi,</hi> of the ſame name by which they cal the <hi>Connies.</hi> wherefore they haue learned vs, howe much we ought to truſt to our fortreſſes, and to the workes of our handes. In like-maner, the men which know not how to keepe order among them ſelues, and which doo no honour nor reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vnto iuſtice, are not ſo wyſe as the <hi>Graſhoppers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the graſhoppers Plin. lib. 1.29</note> For notwithſtanding that they are without King and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, yet neuertheleſſe they kepe an order in flying: And there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſome forme of iuſtice, as thoſe whiche God did ſende into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and there was founde good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der among them. For they flye by great troupes and companies, and do paſſe the long Seas and cuntries. And therefore when the ſcripture woulde ſignifie a great Armie, it ſaith ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time
<pb facs="tcp:5673:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that the armie couereth all the earth, as the <hi>Graſhoppers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudges. 6.5</note> What ſhal we ſay then of thoſe men, whom we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make to obey iuſtice, nor to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their dutie, neither towards god nor towards men? For although that they haue Princes, Maieſtrates, and lawes, and which is more, although that they haue God their ſoueraigne king and father, which neuer ceaſeth to teach &amp; learne them by his word, yet neuertheles, they wil not be kept in order. And although that we haue God for king, and that we are vnder his protection, yet neuertheleſſe we thinke our ſelues to be loſt, aſſone as the protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of men and creatures wanteth. Wherin the <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> ſhew them ſelues more hardie and curra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious then we.<note place="margin">The Spiders Pli. li. 11.24.</note> And what ſhal we ſay of the <hi>spiders,</hi> ought they to geue leſſe ſhame vnto the ſluggardes and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, then the <hi>Ante?</hi> For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that ſhe be but weake, yet neuertheleſſe ſhe feareth not to haunte, not onely poore mens hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but alſo the kinges and princes
<pb facs="tcp:5673:17"/>
Palaces, and to make her webbes in them, turning and winding them now on the one ſide and now on the other,<note place="margin">The wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Spider.</note> and catching al that whiche ſerue her, for to ſtretch them out and make them as long as they can be. And although that one do breake &amp; deface her woorkes, and dryue her from one ſide to the other, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe ſhe is not ſo fearefull that ſhe forſaketh her lodging therefore, but returneth daylie to her woorke: Inſomuche that men doo not ſo faſt breake them, as ſhe repaireth and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth them, ſetting foorth ſtill newe workes. Wherein ſhe maketh men greatly aſhamed, whiche turne them ſelues from their dutie and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice be it thorowe the greatnes and mightineſſe of Kings and Princes, or thorowe all the lettes that men may doe vnto them. Let vs alſo conſider what paine that beaſt taketh to make her threades, for to get her liuing by it. And afterwardes when they are made, what diligence ſhe taketh after her chaſe? Let the ſilke-weauers and
<pb facs="tcp:5673:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
alſo the lynen cloth makers, &amp; the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtrie makers, and imbroderers, and alſo all thoſe that make threddes come, and compare their woorke to the ſpiders webbes, &amp; let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in which is moſt conning. And who hath learned them that occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? It was not men, but rather they haue learned of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> telleth maruayles of their workes, to weete, how they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the labours betweene them, &amp; howe the wyfe ſpinneth and maketh the webbes and threds, and the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band on the other ſide chaſeth and hunteth for their nourriſhment. I thinke that the ſame was the cauſe wherefore the poetes haue fayned that <hi>Arachne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Arachne transformed into a ſpider.</note> that good and cunning weauer, was transformed into a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> becauſe of her Arte, who was founde to haue followed the <hi>Spiders:</hi> of which transformation <hi>Ouid</hi> hath written after this maner.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5673:18"/>
                  <l>And when minarue ſhould depart,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Ouid meta. lib. 6.</note>with iuice of <hi>Hecats</hi> flower:</l>
                  <l>She ſprinkled her, and by and by,</l>
                  <l>the poyſon had ſuch power,</l>
                  <l>That with the touch thereof her heare,</l>
                  <l>her eares and noſe did fade:</l>
                  <l>And very ſmal it both her head,</l>
                  <l>and al her body made.</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of legges, to both her ſides,</l>
                  <l>ſticke fingers ſoft and fine:</l>
                  <l>The reſt is bellie from the which,</l>
                  <l>ſhe neuertheleſſe doth twyne.</l>
                  <l>A ſlender threed, and practiſeth,</l>
                  <l>in ſhape of ſpider ſtill</l>
                  <l>The ſpinners and the webſters craftes:</l>
                  <l>of which ſhe earſt had ſkil.</l>
               </q>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs leaue of the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations of the poets, and returne vnto the ſchoole of the <hi>Spiders,</hi> to which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſendeth vs. Then if we conſider the huſwiferie whiche the ſpider holdeth,<note place="margin">Euil huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues.</note> howe manie euil huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes ſhal we finde, which knowe not how to ſpinne, nor ſewe, neither the arte of weauing, nor yet any ſcience at all for to occupie them ſelues in
<pb facs="tcp:5673:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their houſes? Wherefore ſuch women are not worthie to be compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Spider,</hi> ſauing as touching the poyſon which they are ful of. Alſo if men wil glory and boaſt them ſelues in hunting,<note place="margin">The chaſe &amp; hunting of men and of the ſpiders. Plini. lib. 11. cap. 24. Ariſt. hiſt. animal. lib. 9 cap. 39.</note> and for that they are ſo ingenious and wyſe that they knowe the meanes to take al kind of beaſts, what matter of glorying &amp; boaſting haue they more greater then the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi> For what hunters are there more ſubtil, then the <hi>Spider</hi> for to lye in waite, and for to trappe and ſnare the beaſtes, and to make them to fall into their nettes, or more diligent to lay holde on them? And yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſhe hath neither ſinewes nor bones, But a very litle bodie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>Although it be ſo as thou ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, yet neuertheleſſe, ſhe hath the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie to ſtay &amp; catch ſometims litle euets, &amp; lezards, in her nets. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſaith, is not the worke of the <hi>Spiders</hi> greatly to be maruailed at, which haue geuen vnto wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pattern for to make their thredes, &amp; vnto the fyſher me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for to make their
<pb facs="tcp:5673:19"/>
netts. Let one beholde the perfection &amp; the ſubtilitie of the threde, and the knotes of the webbe that cannot be vnloſed, being as a ſoft and tender skinne, &amp; glewed together as though it were ſtarched. Furthermore, the dying of the colour declareth ſome ayrie and troubled thing, to the end it may the better deceiue. Finally, a man would neuer haue beleued that they had been ſo wel taught to draw together the lines which gouerneth their workes, in ſomuch, that as ſone as there is any praye or captiue, they feele and perceiue it, &amp; in a moment leape out and drawe together their nettes, as doth an expert and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hunter. And if it were not but, that we ſee it daylie before our eyes, a man would thinke that it were but a fable. Behold the witnes of <hi>Plutark.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Beſides al that which we haue alredie ſpoken of, they haue yet another great aduantage. For if men wil chaſe and hunt, there muſt be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, and that they muſt haue many inſtrumentes for their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the which wil be great charge vnto them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>That is very true. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer,<note place="margin">Hunters ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp by their dogs.</note> they muſt nurriſh and feede a great companie of dogges, the which often-times eate vp their maiſters. Euen as the Poets haue written,<note place="margin">The tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Acteon.</note> that the dogges of <hi>Acteon</hi> did eat vp their maiſter, being changed into an hart: of whiche transformation <hi>Ouid</hi> hath written after this maner.
<q>
                     <l>Diana makes no farther threats,<note place="margin">Ouid. meta lib. 3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>but by and by doth ſpread:</l>
                     <l>A paire of liuely old hartes hornes:</l>
                     <l>vpon his ſprinkeled head,</l>
                     <l>She ſharpes his eares, ſhe makes his necke,</l>
                     <l>both ſlender long and lanke:</l>
                     <l>She turnes his fingers into feete,</l>
                     <l>his armes to ſpindle ſhanke.</l>
                     <l>She wrappes him in a hairie hide,</l>
                     <l>be-ſet with ſpeckled ſpottes,</l>
                     <l>And planteth in him fearefulnes,</l>
                     <l>and ſo away he trottes.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5673:20"/>
And afterwardes towardes the ende he ſaith.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Acteon</hi> nowe was ful of care,</l>
                  <l>of ſorowe and of griefe:</l>
                  <l>And blamed much his hornes,</l>
                  <l>which did betray him as a theefe.</l>
                  <l>As often as they named him,</l>
                  <l>he ſadly ſhooke his head:</l>
                  <l>And faine he woulde haue ben away,</l>
                  <l>thence in ſome other ſtead.</l>
                  <l>But there he was, and wel he coulde,</l>
                  <l>haue founde in hart to ſee:</l>
                  <l>His dogges fel dedes, ſo that to feele,</l>
                  <l>in place he had not bee.</l>
                  <l>They hem him in on euery ſide,</l>
                  <l>and in the ſhape of ſtagge:</l>
                  <l>With greedie teeth and griping pawes,</l>
                  <l>their lorde in peeces dragge.</l>
                  <l>So fierce was cruell Phaebes wrath,</l>
                  <l>it coulde not be alayde:</l>
                  <l>Til of his fault by bitter death,</l>
                  <l>the ranſome he had paide.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Beholde as touching the faining of the poets. But yet we muſt not think that it is altogether vaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:5673:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Although the hunters be not in very deede turned into hartes, yet there are a great many of whom one may rightly ſay, that their doggs haue eaten and deuoured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And we muſt not doubt, but that gods iudgment is iuſt herein. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the hunters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted none other fault, but in theſe that they geue vnto the dogges that which woulde nouriſhe, and feede agreat many of poore people, that fault is great ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for to prouoke vpon them, not the ire and wrath of <hi>Diana,</hi> as it is written of <hi>Acteon,</hi> but that of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. And further-more, there is yet another euill, whiche is, that the hunters al the while they beſtow and looſe in hunting, cannot employ the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to their labour and tilling of their groundes, or to woorke vpon any other their occupation. For after that they are once geuen and addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto it, they deſpiſe their houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes and their affayres and doings, and are not ſo carefull as they ought to be. Whereby it commeth to paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5673:21"/>
that afterwards they fal into pouerty &amp; neede. Wherfore one may wel ſay, that not onely their dogges, but alſo their haukes &amp; horſes haue eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not onely becauſe they haue beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed al their ſubſtance and goods to nurriſhe them, but alſo becauſe that thorowe the occaſion of them they are become euil huſbandes, and haue lefte and foreſlowed their chiefeſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres and buſines.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>That which thou ſpeakeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth well with the expoſition,<note place="margin">Palepha. de fabul. natra.</note> the which <hi>Palephatus</hi> geueth of the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of <hi>Acteon,</hi> which we haue ſpoken of. For firſt of al he ſaith, that the poetes geue vs to vnderſtande by this fable, that men ought to take heede that they do nothing whiche may diſpleaſe the gods, and prouoke them to anger. Afterwardes he ſaith that in times paſt, all men labored with their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; did not their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by ſeruants &amp; ſtrange people, but by them ſelues. And therfore al thoſe whiche were diligent in labour were rich. And the more they buſied them
<pb facs="tcp:5673:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſelues, the richer they waxed. And on the other ſide, thoſe that were idle &amp; ſlothful, &amp; the proud which ſhunned labour, and were aſhamed of it, and which gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnto hunting &amp; vnto other paſtimes, became pore &amp; beggers, as he ſaid happened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Acteon,</hi> for the cauſes before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. And therefore he was made a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prouerbe, who afterwards did geue matter vnto the fables and faynings of the Poetes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>There are yet at this day many houſes not onely of rich Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, but alſo of rich yeomen, and huſbandmen, whiche haue been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed partely by ſuch meanes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>We may ſee it before our eyes. And therefore I am of the ſame aduiſe with <hi>Palephatus.</hi> And I doe not think but that the poets haue fained this chaunging of <hi>Acteon</hi> that great hunter chaunged into an harte, and deuoured by his dogges, but for to ſignifie the follie of a great many of fooliſh hunters, which deſtroy them ſelues by their hunting and feeding
<pb facs="tcp:5673:22"/>
their dogges. And if that be to be condemned in gentlemen, whiche make it a daylie occupation, it is yet more to be condemned in laborers and artificers, when they leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done their workes and buſines, for to geue them ſelues vnto ſuch occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiche wil bring them to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie. But let vs returne agayne vnto the <hi>Spider,</hi> whom we talked of, ſhe is a better houſholder, then thoſe are whom we ſpake of. For fyrſt, ſhe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by her hunting, as of her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per occupation, and ſhe leaueth not of her occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by which ſhe liueth, for to vſe any other whiche woulde make her dye with hunger. Agayne, ſhe exercyſeth her hunting all alone, and without any coſt at al. Moreouer ſhe knoweth the times and the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fyt for to take her veniſon, and the places where ſhe muſt pytch her nettes.<note place="margin">Spiders are Aſtrologers Plini. lib. 11 cap. 24. Ariſt. hiſt. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal. lib. 9. cap. 38.39.</note> For ſhe is an Aſtrologer, and knoweth when it wil rayne and the water encreaſe, then ſhe pytcheth her nettes higher. Alſo they make their webbs in cloudie and darke wether,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not in cleare weather, becauſe that the cloudie wether is beſt for to take the beaſtes. And therefore when you ſee a great multitude of them, they ſignifie rayne. We may adde vnto theſe beaſtes, the ſilke wormes,<note place="margin">The ſilke wormes. Plini. lib. 11. cap. 22.23. Ariſt. hiſt. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal. lib. 5. cap. 24.</note> of whiche the Philoſophers haue alſo written maruaylous thinges, that is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the maner of making their neſtes, and of their wolles and webbs with which they do make men and women braue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>What is he that will not greatly maruayle of the wiſedome of God, when he beholdeth the induſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, the ſence and vnderſtanding which is in thoſe litle beaſtes? For if there be ſo much in one ſo litle abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, as is the ſame of the <hi>Ante</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> that with much adoe one can ſcant perceiue with the eye, let vs thinke what is the wyſedome and prouidence of the Creator, whiche hath created them? Let vs alſo thinke whether ſaint Paul had not iuſt cauſe to ſay,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20</note> 
                  <hi>that his eternal power and Godhead is knowen by the viſible thinges.</hi> Where
<pb facs="tcp:5673:23"/>
are the Epicures whiche denie the prouidence of God?<note place="margin">The vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prouidence of God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted in the little creatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pycures.</note> If there be ſo-much in thoſe litle <hi>Ants,</hi> and in thoſe other litle creatures, for to preſerue and keepe their kinde, what ought it to be in God, for to Preſerue his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures and workes of his handes, and cheefely mankinde, whome he hath created to immortalitie? Are theſe wicked epicures worthie to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto theſe beaſtes? Haue not we iuſt occaſion to ſende them to their ſchoole to diſpute with them, and for to learne in the ſame, for to knowe God, and his prouidence? What ſaieſt thou to it <hi>Tobie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>I thinke that we haue as good an occaſion as <hi>Salomon</hi> had, to ſende thither the ſluggarde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>Furthermore, if we will compare the <hi>Ante</hi> and thoſe other beaſtes which we ſpeake of but now, and alſo the order of their common wealth, with al that which <hi>Plato, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon, Ariſtotle,</hi> and the other Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers haue written in their <hi>Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomickes</hi> and politickes, of the lawes,
<pb facs="tcp:5673:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
rule and gouernement of houſes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, common-welthes, citties, and kingdomes, and alſo the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Oeconomikes,</hi> and politicks which euer haue beene among men, men ſhalbe found more beaſtes then they, and more worthie to be ſent vnto their ſchooles, then vnto the ſcholes of the Philoſophers. For the philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers are many tymes like vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preachers, which preach very wel, and ſpeake very earneſtly againſt the deedes of the fleſhe, but they worke but euilly, and they are thoſe whiche do the leaſt of that which they teach others. But theſe ſchoole-maſters to whom the holy ghoſt ſendeth vs by his holy ſcriptures, are maſters which teache their diſciples and ſchollers not in vaine &amp; babling bookes, and which tende al to Pleaſure, but in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that which they teach, for they teach by their owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The whiche maner of teaching, hath more authoritie and maieſtie, then the other, and hath more ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to moue and induce men to that
<pb facs="tcp:5673:24"/>
whereunto they woulde induce and bring them. And as touching that which hath ben ſayde of gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the which manifeſteth it ſelfe in the nature the which he gaue vnto the creatures, it manifeſteth it ſelfe, yet better in that, that the leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt them, are thoſe vnto whom he geueth moſt induſtrie and wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to the ende that by the ſame they may recompence the force and ſtrength whiche is wanting in them. Art not thou of mine opinion frend <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>Experience teacheth vs that thou ſayeſt. But ſeeing we are entreed into talke of good houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I thinke we haue one point to talke of, whiche is very requiſite, not onely in al thoſe whiche woulde be eſteemed for good houſholders, but alſo in al thoſe whiche woulde be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted for humane men, and not for beaſtes more inhumaine then the ſauage and brute beaſtes. The point of whiche I ſpeake, is touching the loue and amitie that the huſband &amp; the wife ought to haue together, and
<pb facs="tcp:5673:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
touching the care that the one ought to haue the one of the other,<note place="margin">The affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fathers and mothers of families, tovvardes ther families</note> and in like maner the fathers and mothers towardes their children. For if thoſe vertues be not in fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of families, what can their houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdes be? Now if it be a queſtion of ſuch vertues, al the beaſtes generally (as <hi>Plutark</hi> witteſſeth) do loue e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tierly that which they ingender and bring forthe, and cheriſh them careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And if there be ſome of the male kynde which haue not that loue nor care, yet it is alwayes founde in the females, &amp; not onely among the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall beaſtes, but alſo among the aquatical &amp; ſeabeaſts. Wherfore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are in hand with the ſchole of beaſts, we may yet ſend men thither, touching that poynt. For that cauſe (but that I feare I ſhall wearie you) I could declare vnto you a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of examples touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of many beaſtes which haue a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular affection and induſtry in ſuche matters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>So that I may take pleaſure in it, I am wel aſſured that <hi>Theophraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:5673:25"/>
will alſo agree vnto it. For I take you both for my maſters. Wherfore I am content to learne of you both, whatſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe you to teach me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The pyge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>Firſt of all, I will ſpeake of the pygeons, both the male and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, becauſe we haue a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in them, of the Amitie which ought to be betwene the huſband &amp; the wife, and of the care that the one ought to haue the one of the other, and afterwardes both of them togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the young ones which God geueth them. For the cocke pygeons in this poynt differ from the nature of the male partridges, for the males of the partridges breake their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males eges, &amp; fiinally their femals do looſe them, becauſe they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them all the while they hatch: And therefore they forſake them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>Then thou canſt not ſette them forth vnto vs for an example of good houſehoulders and good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands,<note place="margin">Euil huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes.</note> but rather for an example of euill husbands which loue not their
<pb facs="tcp:5673:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
wyues, but as the whoremaſters their whoores, to wit, for the onely cauſe of carnal pleaſure, that they may haue with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>And therefore I ſet forth the male pygeons for a contrarye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.<note place="margin">Good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes.</note> For they doe take with their females a part of the care and paine, that they muſt haue of their egges &amp; young. For they kepe the eggs when nede is, Alſo they feede their young, And when the female tarieth ouer long in the feeldes, they flappe them with their winges, and compel them to come vnto their young.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>All huſbandes and wiues, and all fathers and mothers of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, do not agree ſo well together to bring vp their children, and to keepe in good order their houſholdes. For it happeneth often tymes, that the one layeth al the charge vpon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For howe many husbandes are there whiche are euill houſholders, whiche haue no care at all of their houſholdes, neyther of their wyues, and children, but leaue al the charge
<pb facs="tcp:5673:26"/>
vnto their wiues? Howe many alſo are there of women, that do the like towardes their husbandes. But this is yet worſe, when that neyther the one nor the other do their dutie, but let al alone, not caring for any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſvval<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lovves. Plutarke.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>The <hi>Swallowes</hi> alſo haue this propertie, among other byrdes, that they teach their yong, ſo that they know howe to caſt out their donge from their neſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke the other byrdes do the like?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>It is very true, that they are not ſo filthie as men: and their yonge are not ſo defiled with their doung and fylth, as the yong children are with theirs: But yet neuertheleſſe, the <hi>Swallowe</hi> hath one ſinguler propertie herein, more then the other birdes haue, if we will geue credite vnto thoſe whiche haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>We may better knowe that which the ſwallowe doth in ſuche a caſe, then we may knowe of other byrdes, becauſe they dwel not ſo nere
<pb facs="tcp:5673:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as the <hi>Swallowes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>It is very true. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the induſtrie to keepe their yong,<note place="margin">The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge. Plutarke.</note> the partridges vſe in the ſame a great ſubtiltie. For al the while that their yong ones ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not yet fly for their yong age, they accuſtom the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lye v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their backes, &amp; to couer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with moſſe or leaues, or with ſome other thing, when the hunters are hard by them: and in the meane tyme they leade the hunters to the other ſide, and turne and flye as though it were paynefull vnto them, and make as though they could not runne, and they do it ſo long vntill they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred, and drawen the hunters very farre from their yongones.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Beholde a great ſubtiltie, ioyned with a greatloue, and care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her yong-ones.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>That which we reade of the <hi>Hares,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The hares. Plutarke.</note> to that ſame purpoſe is no leſſe worthie to be wondred at. For the hares before they betake them ſelues to their formes, do carie their yong, one in one place, another in another place: And ſome-times they ſeperate
<pb facs="tcp:5673:27"/>
them a good forlong the one from the other, to the ende that if parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture their come eyther man, or dogge, they are not al of them in like da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. And after that they haue made great ſcraping with their feete, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a great leape, they keepe them ſelues there and take their reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>I would neuer haue thought that the hares had been ſo wyſe and ſubtyl, to keepe their yong-ones.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The hedge-hogs.</note>If the hare be wyſe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til in keeping of her yong, the Hedg-hogges are no leſſe, not onely for to prouide for theirs, but alſo for to ſaue and defend them ſelues. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, here what <hi>Plutarke</hi> hath written. Firſt he ſayth, that the ſubtiltie of the Hedg-hogge hath geuen place vnto this prouerbe.<note place="margin">A prouerbe of the fox &amp; of the hedg-hog.</note> The <hi>Fox</hi> hath many wyles, but the Hedg-hogge knoweth one exellent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>It is alſo ſayde that the <hi>Cat</hi> is more wylie then the <hi>Fox.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>There is more reaſon of the ſaying of the <hi>Hedg-hogge.</hi> For when the <hi>Fox</hi> purſueth him, the <hi>Hedg-hogge</hi> rowleth
<pb facs="tcp:5673:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
him ſelfe (as men ſay) within his pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, as the Cheſtnut is encloſed with in his hull. And by that meanes he kepeth him there encloſed, ſo that he cannot be any whit hurted. But the care &amp; the wyſedome, that he hath of his yong-ones, is worthie to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at. For as <hi>Plutarke</hi> witneſſeth, he goeth into the vineyards in the time of cutting, and with his feete he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the ground the grapes, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes he rowleth him-ſelfe vpon them, and maketh them to ſticke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his prickles. <hi>Plutarke</hi> who hath written ſo, bringeth in a man who witneſſed, that he did ſee it with his eyes. And therefore he ſayth, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that on a certayne day, we ſawe one, that we did thinke that it was a Grape tree, which went, he was ſo loden with grapes. And when he is entred into his denne and hole,<note place="margin">The Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie and pronoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hedghog.</note> he geueth one part to his yong-ones, &amp; keepeth the other for him ſelfe. For his hole or borrowe hath two en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trings in, the one towards the north, and the other towardes the South
<pb facs="tcp:5673:28"/>
winde, the which he ſtoppeth and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, according as he ſeeth the times do chaunge, as the mariners do the ſayles of their ſhippes. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a certayne man of <hi>Cyzicenia,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good heede thereunto, did get by that meanes, a great renowne, as though he could foreſhewe by Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie, what windes would blowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>That man of whom thou ſpeakeſt, may wel aduaunce &amp; bragg him ſelfe, that he hath paſſed maſter in aſtronomie, and in the art of prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications in the ſchoole of the <hi>Hedg-hogge:</hi> Seeing that by his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he hath gotten ſuche a fame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ignorant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome,</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt true. But ſith that we haue ſpoken of beaſts, which are conuerſant and dwelling vpon the earth: I will ſay alſo ſome-thing of thoſe which haunt the waters, and lyue there, and chiefely in the Sea, &amp; I will firſt begin, by a ſea byrde, called <hi>Halcion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Halcion. faithfullnes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n houſhold.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutark</hi> among others, telleth of his great vertues. For firſt he ſaith, that this byrde loueth ſingulerly his
<pb facs="tcp:5673:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
femal: &amp; ioineth not himſelf with her at certaine times onely, but at al tims of the yeere, and not for that he is ſo much geuen vnto <hi>luxurie:</hi> For he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath the companie of any other. But he doth the ſame thorowe ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and good wil, as it behoueth huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes to do. When the male is old, &amp; that he followeth his female with great payne, ſhe taketh care on him, and beareth and nurriſheth him, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer leauing him behind her. For ſhe carrieth him vpon her ſhoulders, and leadeth him whether it pleaſeth him, and keepeth and cheriſheth him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vntil death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>A man ſhal finde very fewe ſuch wyues, which are ſo faythful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their husbandes, and which haue ſuch care ouer them, and ſo long.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>I do not denie but that we ſhal find many good husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; good wyues, who do ſufficiently their dutie the one towardes the other, if we wil make compariſon with thoſe whiche do euilly diſcharge their office in ſuche a caſe. But thoſe here are very
<pb facs="tcp:5673:29"/>
thicke ſowen, in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of others And after we haue to note, that the beaſtes which I ſpeake of, haue this more then men: That is, that there is not only ſome of them in their kind, which gouerne them ſelues ſo, but al are ſo by nature, and followe it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any fault, becauſe that they are not corrupted thorowe ſin, as the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which maketh them more beaſtes, then the beaſtes. But marke yet more what this author hath writ ten of the care that this byrde hath, to prepare lodging for his yong-ones.<note place="margin">The build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Halcion.</note> The mother (ſayth he) hath ſuch great care ouer her yong-ones, that aſſoone as ſhe feeleth her ſelfe great, ſhe beginneth to builde. She heapeth not the claye and lome agaynſt the walles, and the myre as the <hi>Swallowes</hi> do, neither chargeth al her me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers as the honie bees do, when they make their combs, deuiding their worke &amp; their chambers in faſhion, hauing ſix ſquares and as many feete: But the <hi>Halcion</hi> employeth but one organ, &amp; one ſimple inſtrument, that is her
<pb facs="tcp:5673:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
byll: and not hauing any ayde, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and care towards her yong-ones, ioyned and added to her induſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. O good God, what doth ſhe? What taketh ſhe in hande? It is harde to be beleeued of thoſe, which haue not ſeene it. For ſhe maketh a worke after a newe faſhion, much like vnto a ſhippe, the which cannot be broken neither drowned with the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ues &amp; ſurges. For ſhe maketh and tyeth it together, with the bones and pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of litle fiſhes, and ioyneth them the one within the other: ſome right, others croſſe: As we ſee howe cloth is wouen. And after that ſhe hath ioyned and faſtned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo together, ſhe bendeth &amp; turneth them round? And at the laſt, ſhe maketh it after ſuch ſorte, that it ſeemeth properly that it is a ſhippe, pycked and narrow in the bottome, and wide aboue, or els a long fiſhing boate. After that ſhe hath finiſhed it, ſhe bringeth it to the ſea ſhore, &amp; ſetteth it by the ſea-ſide, and when the ſea beginneth to flowe and beat ſoftly agaynſt it, it teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:5673:30"/>
her to ſtoppe the holes and ventes, and to amende and make ſtrong that which is weake. Nowe after that al is very ſtrong and ſounde, ſhe ſhutteth it ſo faſt, that neyther ſtone nor iron can breake it. But in al the woorke there is not a thing more worthie to be maruailed at, then is the dooer of the ſayde worke. For it is made after ſuch ſort, that none can enter but ſhe onely. The other beaſtes can neyther ſee nor perceiue it, yea and the water cannot enter into it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias,</speaker>
               <p>Thou telleſt me of incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thinges. If that which thou ſaieſt bee true, the <hi>Halcions</hi> haue rather taught men the manner to make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes &amp; boates, then the <hi>Halcions</hi> haue learned of them the ſcience &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they haue to builde their houſes, as well for them ſelues as for their yong-ones, the which may flote and ſwimme vppon the Sea, as the ſhippes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>I boaſt not that I haue ſene that which I ſpeake of. But <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarke</hi> who hath written it, alleadgeth
<pb facs="tcp:5673:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for witneſſe of ſuch things, marriners which dwell in the Iles, haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeene the experience of thoſe thinges, which he hath written,<note place="margin">Of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight &amp; care of the fiſhes tovvardes their ftuite and young.</note> aſwel of this byrd <hi>Halcion,</hi> as of the fiſhes, of which he maketh a great diſcourſ. For he praiſeth greatly ſome Seafiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es for their foreſight, and care that they haue of their fruites and young, aſwell in their procreation and birth as in the nouriſhment, keeping and preſeruation of them. And therefore he ſaith touching this matter: Firſt, that all the fiſhes which inhabite the Seas neere vnto anye lakes, or into which riuers do come, following the ſame riuers, do ſeeke earneſtly (when the time approcheth that they muſt bring forth thir fruite) the ſweeteſt waters, and thoſe that haue leaſt ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: &amp; they do the ſame for two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to wit, either becauſe that tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie is beſt for them to yeelde their fruit, or els becauſe that the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and riuers are leſſe daungerous becauſe of the beaſtes, and alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they maye beſt nouriſhe their
<pb facs="tcp:5673:31"/>
fruites. Wherefore many bring forth and caſt their fruites in the Eginian ſea: For it hath not in it any whalles, but onely little Dolphus, &amp; little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calues: And the great riuers that run into it, giue a ſweete and gentle tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratenes and moſt pleaſaunt to the fiſhes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias</speaker>
               <p>Behold a good foreſight, it wanteth a great deale, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know ſo well to prouide for their families, in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>And by and by after <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarke</hi> ſaith. And although that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture that is common vnto all mothers, to haue care of that whiche they haue engendred: yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the males doe not murther and kill their younge, as <hi>Ariſtotimis</hi> hath ſayd: But which is more, they take ſuch great care, that they wil not ſtur from them, and do geather and heap to geather the egs, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth. There be alſo ſome which follow the females, and ſprinkle the egges, with the genitall ſeed, becauſe without the ſame nothing can growe excellent
<pb facs="tcp:5673:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and perfect, but wil abide imperfect, and wil not growe as it ought to do. Commonly the fiſhes whiche we call <hi>Phyces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phyces.</note> hauing made as it were a knot of an hearbe whiche we call <hi>Algue,</hi> put it about their yong, and it defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them from the tempeſtes. But the lampries do beare the bel,<note place="margin">The lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prey.</note> and do merite the crowne aboue all other fiſhes in caſe of fatherly loue, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, goodnes and gentlenes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their yong-ones. Firſt they do lay their egges, and then the litle ones. But they do not caſt forth their yong as other fiſhes do, but nurriſh them in their bellies, as though they engendred them twiſe: And when they are growen, then they caſt them foorth, and teach them to ſwymme &amp; play about them. And afterwardes they receiue them agayne into their bellies in at their mouthes, and geue vnto them their bodies for to dwell in, geuing them place, meate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, vntil ſuch time as they knowe that they are able to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:5673:32"/>
               <speaker>Tobias</speaker>
               <p>If it be ſo as thou ſaieſt the ſea beaſtes doe ſurmount and paſſe the beaſtes of the earth, in that loue &amp; care towards their fruite &amp; young.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>Thou wilt maruaile more of this, that the ſame Aucthour hath written touching this matter, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Tortic</hi> of which he ſpeaketh thus.<note place="margin">The tortice.</note> The care alſo that the <hi>Tortice</hi> hath to nouriſh &amp; keep her yongons, is worthy of great admiration, for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping alitle out of the ſea, ſhe bringeth forth her yong. And becauſe that ſhe cannot continue long out of the ſea, and ſtay vpon the lande, ſhee layeth firſt her egges vpon the ſand, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhe couereth them with fine ſande, &amp; after that ſhe hath couered them wel, (as ſome ſay) ſhe marketh the place, and ſigneth it with her feet, ſo that ſhe may finde it agayne, or as others ſay, the femall being ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by her male, printeth vpon the ſande, the carecter and forme of her owne ſhel. After-wardes, whiche is a thing greatly to be maruayled, fortie daies being paſt ſhe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth agayne:
<pb facs="tcp:5673:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for ſo long time the yong muſte bee ſhut vp. And when the male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male are come, euery one of them knowing their treaſure, vncouereth it more ioyfully and cherefully then men vncouer the holes and places in whiche they haue hid vp their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. <hi>Plutarke</hi> calleth the treaſure of the Tortice their eggs &amp; their yong, becauſe that there is no man ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his treaſures, and which loueth them ſo much as the Tortice loueth, and is careful of her yong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>It is ſayd in a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe,<note place="margin">A prouerbe.</note> that thoſe that come from farre, haue greater libertie to tell what they liſt, then others. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that one cannot eaſily gaineſay that which they ſpeake, they haue the greater licence to lye. We may ſay the lyke of thoſe which ſpeake of the ſea and of the Sea beaſtes, vnto thoſe which knowe not what they are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>I require thee not that thou ſhouldeſt beleeue as the Goſpell, al that I ſhall rehearſe vnto thee of <hi>Ariſtotle, Plinie</hi> and of <hi>Plutarke,</hi> and of
<pb facs="tcp:5673:33"/>
ſuch other. But yet neuertheleſſe I do not thinke, but that thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men hauing writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe things that they haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that there are ſome things therein trew, &amp; that they haue had ſome experience, or els ſome good witneſſes thereof. Fot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they were learned men, and of great aucthoritie, and renowme, we muſt not thinke that they haue written at all aduenture, for to cauſe them ſelues to be mocked at, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wel that their writinges ſhoulde be well examined by many learned men, and which haue tryed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the thinges, whereof they haue written. Wherefore we muſt not by and by reiect as fables, all that which we our ſelues haue not ſene, &amp; which is ſtraunge vnto vs. For God is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous in his creatures and in his workes, the whiche he woulde not haue them to be altogether couered and kept ſecret. And therefore he would be ſerued of the <hi>Painims,</hi> which haue enquired of the ſecretes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for to manifeſt vnto vs many of
<pb facs="tcp:5673:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his maruailes, to the ende we might alwayes haue more matter to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in his prouidence. And therefore to conclude this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I wil yet declare vnto thee, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter, that which <hi>Plutark</hi> hath written of the ſea-keyne,<note place="margin">The ſea-keine.</note> after this ſorte. The ſea-kyne (ſayth he) do bring foorth their young vpon the ſande: And when they waxe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing great, they carrie them into the ſea, as for to taſte of it, afterwards they bring them agayne vpon the ſande, and do ſo many tymes, vntyll ſuch time as they know that they can helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, &amp; to take pleaſure in the ſea. <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſaith, that if one would fill at ones, a Phiole or glaſſe whiche hath a narrowe necke,<note place="margin">Quintillian. inſtit. reth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lib. 1.</note> and would powre in at once the liquore that he would put into it, it will not enter, but will ſprinkle abroade heere and there. But if one would fill it by litle and litle, and as drop by drop, he ſhall fill it eaſiely, and ſhall looſe nothing of that hee powreth into it, <hi>Quintilian</hi> vſeth this compariſon for
<pb facs="tcp:5673:34"/>
to giue vs to vnderſtand, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to vſe ſuch beginning,<note place="margin">The meanes that vve muſt vſe in teaching.</note> in the inſtruction of thoſe whom we haue to teach, and chiefely of young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. For they cannot comprehende at once all that one can teach them. Wherefore we muſt goe by litle and litle. On the other ſide, it is in lyke maner very harde to vſe them ſelues ſodainely to one thing, to the which they haue not been vſed vnto, and chiefely when it is newe and ſtrange. Wherefore it behoueth to keepe meanes, and to do by litle and litle that, that one cannot doe at once.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>There be a great many which haue not yet that diſcretion &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For they would haue thoſe with whom they haue to doe, ſhould be perfect at the firſt daſhe, and that they ſhoulde knowe in one day or in one moneth, that which they cannot vnderſtande them ſelues in a yeere. There are alſo many fathers,<note place="margin">the fault of fathers and mothers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardes their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> whiche make their children to diſpayre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they preſſe and charge them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue meaſure, and require of them
<pb facs="tcp:5673:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more then they are able: As alſo to the contrary, there are others which haue not ſuch care and diligence to teach their children, as they ought, nor to keepe them vnder good diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, but let them haue ſo much their wil, that they are quite marred and ſpoyled.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>And therefore we ſhall haue iuſt occaſion to ſende the firſt to the ſchoole of the ſea-kyne. For they are more calues then the kyne and bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes. I ſay aſmuch of the maiſters of ſchools, which know not to teach their ſcholers, by good methoode, and order. As touching the other which endeuour the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues nothing at all to teach their children, I ſende them vnto the ſchoole of the <hi>Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Crocodile.</note> if that beaſte were not ſo cruel, But yet neuertheleſſe take away the crueltie, yet ſhe declareth that ſhe wil not ſuffer her yong-ones, except they haue courage, and except they will robbe and ſteale. And therefore the mother kylleth him, which at his firſt going foorth, he neither ſtealeth
<pb facs="tcp:5673:35"/>
nor deuoureth, eyther a frogge, or a ſnayle, or ſome litle graſſe, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch thing which commeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. On the contrary, ſhe loueth the coragious, and loueth them, as <hi>Plutarke</hi> ſaith, not with a fooliſhe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as the fooliſhe mothers doe, but thorow iudgement, as the moſt wyſeſt of the worlde haue vſed to do. Although that that crueltie of the <hi>Crocodile</hi> is to be diſpiſed: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe this is to be prayſed, that the mother is not ſo fooliſhe ouer her yong-ones, that ſhe ſupporteth them if they be other then they ought to be according to their kinde. But we haue ſpoken ſufficiently of the nature of beaſtes, vpon the matter of good and euil houſholders. It nowe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that we make an ende of this matter, except <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> wil ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noother thing for the confirmation hereof.<note place="margin">The inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſaint Paull vnto fathers and mothers.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Theophraſt.</speaker>
               <p>I haue no other thing to ſay at this time, but that Saint Paul geueth a very good rule vnto fathers and mothers, &amp; vnto al thoſe whiche
<pb facs="tcp:5673:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
haue charge of children, yea in a fewe wordes, when he ſayde?<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye fathers, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke not your children to wrath, but bring them vp in inſtruction and information of the Lorde.</hi> And in another place,<note place="margin">Collo. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers prouoke not your children to anger, leaſt they be diſcouraged.</hi> By theſe words he geueth the fathers and mothers wel to vnderſtande, what moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ought to vſe towardes their children, aſwell to the ende they be not altogether diſcouraged, and in diſpaire, as alſo to the ende they mar the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not thorow to great libertie. For when he admoniſheth them to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and correction, he geueth them to vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that they ought not to bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp in idleneſſe, and to let them doo what they liſt, but to holde and kepe them vnder feare and correction. Whereupon we haue to note that he ſayth not onely, bring them vp in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction &amp; information, but he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, of the Lorde. For there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great many, whiche are very good houſholders, for to cauſe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:5673:36"/>
to learne, ſiences, artes and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupations, for to become of ſome good countenaunce in the worlde, and for to get them great honours and riches, or at the leaſt wiſe howe to get their liuing: But they make none accompt, to bring them vp in the feare of God, and in the trewe knowledge of him and his worde, without which, as we haue alredie ſaide from the beginning, that men are more beaſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the brute beaſts. And therefore, he that wil ſhewe him ſelfe a good houſholder and a good father, hauing trew care of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt begin there. For it is not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten without cauſe.<note place="margin">Pſal 111.10. Pro. 1.7.9.10 Galoa. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>That the feare of the Lorde is the beginning, the foundation and head of al wiſedome,</hi> and he can neuer faile to do well, &amp; pleaſe God, which doth feare him. And as touching that which <hi>Ierome</hi> ſayde of the <hi>Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile,</hi> there are many which follow her example, and many more then is needefull.<note place="margin">The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Crocodile.</note> For if their children be not cruell and rauenors, as they are, they thinke them not to be their lawfull
<pb facs="tcp:5673:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
children, but diſauowe and forſake them, as though they were not of their blood. But we muſt not require of our children, that they may be like vnto vs in our vices, but that they &amp; we may be trewly reformed after the image of God, and that we may rule al our life after the rule that he hath ſet foorth vnto vs in his worde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ierome.</speaker>
               <p>Behold a verie good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, vpon which I thinke that <hi>Toby</hi> wil willingly ſtay him ſelfe with vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tobias.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhoulde doe wrong if I ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt it.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
